What's up, guys? It's Clark. Welcome
back to the channel. Everybody's telling
you to let go, but no one tells you how.
And so, in this video, I want to revisit
that topic of letting go in your life.
We're also going to cover a simplified
version of the emotions scale. And then
to speed this up, I want to share three
big blocks that prevent people [music]
from actually letting go and the
solution to each one. All right, so if
that sounds good, smash the like button.
link down below to our free newsletter I
send to you every Saturday with ideas
that can change your life.
So, let's first talk about what's
actually going on inside of you when
we're talking about letting go and set
the goal. Lower emotions you would feel
on a given day are fear, guilt, and
shame. And there's that famous quote
from this book, Paradise Lost, John
Milton. The mind is its own place in
itself and can make a hell out of heaven
or a heaven out of hell. This is
psychological hell. And in that way,
it's like a ball and chain that does
weigh you down. It is emotional baggage.
You've heard that term. They have a lot
of baggage, dude. That will weigh you
down. And this is also why on the flip
side, we like hanging around people who
are funny, who are light, who are
expressive, that raise us up. We'll get
to that in a little bit. All right, the
next trio here. These are better than
these. you'd prefer these, but they're
still, I guess, in the destructive
energy if you live your life here versus
the constructive energy, the creative
energy as I call it. Pride, anger, and
desire. Okay? So, in order for you to
want to better your life or to let go,
you have to desire something. You have
to see it better than it is. But if
you're only stuck in fear, guilt, and
shame, you can't even have that vision
to better your life. And that's the real
sinister part about it. anger. You might
be like, why is that higher than fear
and guilt and shame? Because when you're
angry, you want to do something about
it. That can be motivating. There's a
lot of uh anger to prove yourself or
prove people wrong. That can be very
powerful to tap into to change your
life. You notice a lot of the
motivational content that's targeted
towards beginners is getting them to
feel angry, right there. It's like a
guru screaming at you like you got to
better your life. You got to want
something, you know, as bad as you want
to breathe. You got to hustle. You got
to uh grind. You you grind yourself down
to the smallest piece. And guess what?
That's useful to people who need that.
If they're here, getting angry is a good
way to get yourself out of that. So,
moving up the scale, getting in a better
state, you have emotions of courage,
willingness, and acceptance. Now, these
are better, right? When you have the
courage to move beyond anger, the
courage to actually think for yourself
instead of getting sucked into group
think tribalism that splits us in
duality, you know, paradigms, us versus
them, their their side, our side, our
team, their team. And you can see beyond
that when you have the courage to
elevate yourself and see the different
perspective. Then there's willingness to
change, acceptance. These are also the
gateway to actually start creating.
Okay? Cuz when you're angry or you're in
this state, you're just like a it's hard
to create because you just want to tear
everything down. Haters and people on
the internet and trolls, it's always
from this energy. But when you finally
accept things for what they are, a
musician who finally accepts their style
and uniqueness and they own it instead
of trying to conform and be like someone
else, that's when they create their best
art. When you finally stop trying to
improve yourself and you just accept
yourself for who you are and not being
flawed or broken, that's when you
finally start to come into your own.
Now, for the top emotions, we have
things like reason, love, joy, and
peace. Ultimately, what we're after is
the states of inner peace and love. Now,
let's break down a couple important
points related to this before we give
you the three blocks and ultimately how
to fix this. The biggest misconception
people have with this chart when they
see it is taking this as a goal. They're
like, "Okay, my goal is to stay there
and never go back there. If I ever feel
any of these, then I'm backsliding in
life." That is so unrealistic. And don't
buy any movement or guru who's preaching
that you're just going to get here and
stay there. The full human experience is
to feel everything. Just like all the
notes in a scale, all the colors out
there, you're human. You're going to
bounce around and feel things. You might
have a year where you stay more up here.
You might have a month where you stay
more up here. You might have a day in a
really good month when you're down here.
So the whole point of letting go is
realizing when you're in some of these
emotions, okay, what's causing it? Can
you release that? Can you view it
differently? And it's in the releasing
that you finally can float up and feel
good. Nichza has a banger quote. He
says, "The snake that cannot shed its
skin must perish." So letting go is less
about like adding things in. It's just
more about removing and shedding off the
layers that aren't you. So, now I want
to get into the three blocks that
prevent you from letting go.
So, I'll give you a personal story on
this one. Back in the day, I was super
hooked on jewel pots, EIGs, and I was
smoking the equivalent of two packs of
cigarettes a day of those things. And no
one's smoking thinking they're doing
something for their health. And so, I
told myself I should quit. You know, I I
really got to quit this thing. And I
would try go a couple days and then fall
back. And now there's this whole other
can of worms of guilt and shame. Well, I
tried and I failed and now I'm really
screwed. Until one day I did something
so backwards that helped so much. This
is the biggest one I see people get
stuck in. You're not ready. See, when I
finally admitted to myself after so many
failed attempts of trying to quit
vaping, I just wasn't ready because I
liked having the comfort and the state
change of nicotine. What was so crazy is
all the guilt faded away of doing the
thing because so many bad habits are
perpetuated by guilt and shame, these
low vibe emotions. When you're here,
this is where you drink compulsively
from. This is where you do drugs. This
is where you have tons of bad habits and
doom scroll. If you're compulsively
hiding out with those habits, it's
because it's from here and you feel
guilty and shameful, which just
perpetuates the bad habits. So once I
just admitted to myself the
uncomfortable truth, I wasn't ready to
stop smoking, a lot of the guilt and
shame faded away from it. And what was
easier is shortly after that, because I
didn't have guilt and shame, a lot of
the motivation to do this thing and hide
out with it was gone and I was able to
quit. What I realized in that is a lot
of our bad behaviors are driven out of
shame and guilt. Now, let's take a
different context in your life here.
Relationships. A lot of people are like,
"Well, I can't get over this person."
And the simple fact is that they're not
ready to. I have some backwards advice.
You know, instead of forcing yourself to
get over someone, what if you just
allowed yourself to not get over them?
If nothing else works, try that. Just
allow yourself to be attached to them.
And eventually what's going to happen is
you're going to get so exhausted from
that that you're you're going to have no
choice but to accept it and say, "You
know what? Screw this. Like, I'm I'm
ready to go live my life. I don't want
to be attached to this person anymore.
I'm not even that same person that they
dated." So, what do you do instead?
Well, Carl Jung has his banger quote I
reference on this channel quite a bit.
Your biggest problems in life can't be
solved. They can only be outgrown. And
what he means by that in my
interpretation, you're not trying to
solve your problems so you can raise
this up. You're trying to just outgrow
them and move beyond it. And part of
that is realizing when you're ready and
when you're not. Good on block number
one, knowing when you're not ready and
not judging yourself for not being
ready, but allowing yourself to process
through it on your own time and
definitely not getting sucked into guilt
and shame and judgment, which makes it
way worse. Number two, this is the
second block that prevents you from
dropping things and moving on. Before I
give it to you, you have to understand
one concept. And this will take some of
the weight off personalizing everything
that you feel cuz you have some of these
emotions bubble up and it's easy to
identify them and be like, "Oh, I'm a
fearful person." Or, "Oh, I'm an angry
person who got mad at someone cutting me
off uh you know, when someone cut me off
in traffic." If you're not careful and
you don't check that, it becomes an
identity and makes it worse. The
distinction here is the difference
between primary emotions and secondary
emotions. This comes from EFT therapy.
So, primary emotions are your first
initial reaction. Secondary emotions are
the thing after that. You feel sad cuz
someone's not texting you back and you
really vibed with that person. Well,
that's normal. But the secondary
emotion, this is the damage that we do
to ourselves where we tell ourselves the
story that we're never going to find
anyone again. They were the one that got
away. You know, we're unlovable. We
don't deserve it, etc. It's normal to
feel disappointed. In fact, it's healthy
if you lost a job and you find yourself
in a state of depression. Dude, I'm
freaking out. I don't know what I'm
going to do. Like that. That's all
normal. What's not normal is saying and
I'll never find another job and I'm
going to have to like get on welfare and
I'm a total loser and now you know my
life is in the gutter. Letting go is not
about this this primary emotion that you
feel cuz often times this is automatic.
It might be there for good reason and if
you try to force something you're
actually falling into the suppression
trap. Letting go is about releasing the
secondary emotions and the stories that
come with it, the meaning you're
associating with it. This mistake is you
focus on the primary emotion and not the
secondary meaning. So, if you just stay
on the surface of what you're trying to
let go of, it's never going to go away.
It's just going to bubble back. And this
is where suppression comes in. All
right? This is uh you feel fearful and
you drink and then you don't feel afraid
anymore. Well, then the next time you
feel that fear, if you don't drink,
you're going to feel it. You know, my
favorite analogy, it's like a trash can.
We all have this emotional waste system
down here. And if we never take out the
trash and we just shove it down to make
room for more gunk, it's going to stink
up our whole emotional state. So, the
solution isn't to just ignore it and
shove it down deeper. Suppression,
right? Oh, I feel afraid. Let me just
drink and oh, I don't feel afraid
anymore. Um, oh, I feel lonely. let me
just, you know, pursue superficial
relationships and then I don't feel
lonely anymore. That all just shoves it
down deeper and then it comes back with
the vengeance. The solution is to help
take out your emotional trash. And how
do you do that? You stop focusing on the
primary emotions. You start focusing on
the secondary meaning. It's why I'm such
a fan of journaling. It's like the place
you can go to create new meaning of
stories throughout your life. And once
you start drilling down to the root of
something, it really does change your
perspective on it. Feelings about your
feelings and the meaning you're making
of them. If you feel any of this, go a
level deeper and say, "What does this
mean?" Okay, I'm feeling afraid. What
does this mean? What's the story I'm
telling behind it? And that is the thing
you actually need to do some work around
and let go of. And if we don't, then
we're just going to keep feeling this
feeling and wondering why this whole
process of letting go and growth isn't
working. until I realized the fear of oh
that past relationship didn't work out
and now I'm afraid my clock is running
out I'm going to be lonely or that was
the best person for me they got away and
what that means that's the thing we need
to let go of not the fear of that person
does that make sense when I'm afraid of
pivoting because I invested 10 years of
my life into this thing and I want it to
mean something and if I walk away all
that time is wasted or at least that's
how I perceive it then I'm never going
to walk away from I'm always going to be
afraid and I'm just going to be stuck
instead of doing the inner work and
realizing, oh, those 10 years set me up
for the next thing and I get to transfer
all that experience into this thing
that's going to be better and more
aligned with me. That's an example of an
insight you can get through doing the
inner work or letting go. Oh, that
person we would have never worked out in
a million years and they actually taught
me a lot about what I don't want and
about who I am and now the next
relationship's going to be more aligned
and better. That's an example of how
letting go works. Both of those bump you
up to here with changing your story, the
acceptance and willingness around seeing
something different. There's a lot of
techniques out there that help you
suppress further down and you think
you're making progress with just another
technique. The real inner work takes
courage to peer down to the depths of
your soul and look at yourself in the
mirror and say, you know what, I can be
an I am capable of treating the
person I say I love terribly. There's
people smarter than me. I don't know
everything, right? That level of
humility. And that's the inner work, you
know, not to get too personal here, but
I've been doing for years. And I think
what really opened it up was working
one-on-one with a coach for over a year
who every single week was just that. It
was just someone tearing a part of you
open and just like poking a pencil in
there over and over again. You're like,
"Ah, stop, stop, stop." And you see all
these defense mechanisms kick on, your
ego squirming, and then it finally wears
you down and sits with you for months
and you start becoming open to a new way
of looking at yourself and then the
world. That's what letting go, that's
what growth is. And letting go is
letting go of a part of your identity.
Finally, the last one here that this one
is probably the biggest and it's a huge
misconception. People confuse letting go
with quitting. A lot of people can view
this process of letting go and releasing
as weak. He's a quitter. Especially if
you grew up playing sports. I don't know
about you, but like I was playing sports
and there's that saying, "Oh, quitters
never win and winners never quit." You
got to have grit, perseverance. I want
to share a quote with you on this that I
think can explain it better than I can
concisely. It comes from CS Lewis. I've
been on a bit of a kick of his recently.
We all want progress, but progress means
getting nearer to the place where you
want to be. And if you have taken a
wrong turning, then going forward does
not get you any nearer. If you're on the
wrong road, progress means doing an
about turn and walking back to the right
road. And in that case, the man who
turns back soonest is the most
progressive man. There is nothing
progressive about being pigheaded and
refusing to admit a mistake. Letting go
does not mean quitting. Letting go means
realizing when you're on the wrong path,
you can let go of that without feeling
like a failure. And in doing so, if
you're on the wrong path and you turn
around quickest, you're actually the
most progressive person. You know, I've
known people who have tried the whole
entrepreneur thing and it just didn't
feel right in their soul and then they
go back and get a 9 to5 and that's right
for them and that maybe they like the
idea of entrepreneurship and all the
social media content but the dayto-day
of doing it and being alone they didn't
like and getting a 9 to5 was them
maturing out of this old paradigm and
they were letting go of a story they
were telling themselves about having to
work and be a certain Okay. What does
your next breakthrough require you
stopping? What do you need to let go of
so that you can move forward? We're not
going back on a version of oursel. We're
stepping in to the version we want to
be. All right, guys. We covered a lot
today and I want to recap this with you
and then we'll uh tell you what to do
next here. Your mind makes a heaven of
hell and a hell of heaven if you let it.
There's emotions that are destructive
that will suck you down and keep you in
this downward spiral where life starts
feeling like hell on earth. But then
there's emotions that you can get to
that help you create and express
yourself that spiral you up where life
gets better. Letting go is the process
of releasing stories or people or
anything that's sucking you down here.
And in doing so, you're able to get into
this middle ground where then you can
float up. But there are three things
that block you from that. You're not
ready to actually do it. You might like
the thing you're holding on to, and
until you're ready to fully let go of
it, no amount of techniques or forcing
it will matter. Block two is focusing on
the primary emotion instead of the
secondary meaning. And if your focus is
letting go of any of these only, you'll
suppress it down and fall into unhealthy
coping mechanisms. The meaning behind
these is what you really need to get to,
as that's often the root. And the third
block is viewing letting go as
surrendering and quitting. Being so
pigheaded, so to speak, that we think
we're progressive for just charging
forward, when really being progressive
means doing an about turn if we're on
the wrong road. And the way you do that
is asking yourself, what's that thing I
need to drop and let go of that's
actually progressive and moving me on a
different path? Link down below to our
free newsletter from me to you every
Saturday. What I'll do now is link up
right here a follow-up video for you to
watch if you want to keep this going and
learn more about yourself. Do hard
things. Bet on yourself. Make your
future self proud. base.